<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD DocBk XML V3.1.4//EN"
	"file:///usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<article>


<articleinfo xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Installation Guide</title>
  <abstract>This article includes download, build, and installation instructions specific
  to this software package.</abstract>
</articleinfo>

<edit by="David Hilvert" in-year="2006"/>
<edit by="David Hilvert" in-year="2005"/>
<edit by="David Hilvert" in-year="2004"/>
<edit by="David Hilvert" in-year="2003"/>
<edit by="David Hilvert" in-year="2002"/>

<s><t>Windows Binaries</t>

<s><t>URLs</t>

<ul><li><winurl/>
</li></ul>

</s>
<s><t>Extraction and Use</t>

<p> The zip file available at the above URL is an archive containing the ALE
executable; a zip archival utility can be used to extract the executable from
the archive.  </p>

<p> Once extracted, since ALE is a command-line program, it may be necessary to
open a command prompt window to use ALE successfully.  For more information
about command-line usage and options, see the User Manual.  </p>
</s>

</s>

<s><t>Compiling from source</t>

<s><t>URLs</t>

<ul><li><sourceurl/>
</li></ul>

</s>

<s><t>Build prerequisites</t>

<s><t>GCC C++ compiler</t>

<p> GCC version 3.2.3 with C++ support is known to build ALE successfully.  Older
versions of GCC may fail to compile some versions of ALE.</p>

</s>

<s><t>Prerequisites for building on Windows</t>

<p> Successfully running the configuration script on Windows (e.g., for native
builds) may require installation of Cygwin.  For more information on Cygwin,
see:</p>

<ul><li><ulink url="http://www.cygwin.com/"/>
</li></ul>

<p>Alternatively, this package can be cross-compiled for Windows on a non-Windows
architecture, provided that the appropriate cross-compilers and libraries are
available.</p>

</s>

</s>

<s><t>Extraction</t>

<p>Download the source archive file from the URL indicated in the section
'URLs', and invoke:</p>

<ll>tar xzf <sourcepacktargz/>
cd <sourcepack/>
</ll>

<p>Invoking 'ls configure' afterward should reveal an executable script
'configure'.  This script is used to determine the capabilities of the system
that will run the software.</p>

</s>

<s><t>Running configure</t>

<p>This package uses a configuration script, 'configure', generated by the GNU
project build tools ("autotools").  For most cases, it should be sufficient to
invoke:</p>

<ll>./configure
make
make install
</ll>

<p>In cases where the defaults are not adequate, configuration options can be
passed to the configuration script.</p>
</s>

<s><t>Configuration options</t>

<p>Configuration options can be passed to the 'configure' script prior to build
and installation, as:</p>

<ll>./configure --config-option1 --config-option2 ...
make
make install
</ll>

<p>Options specific to this package are described in the following subsections.
General configuration options are described in the file 'INSTALL' included in
the source package.</p>

<s><t>ImageMagick Support</t>

<p>Enabling ImageMagick support allows ALE to make use of the file-handling
capabilities of ImageMagick ( <ulink url="http://imagemagick.org/"/> ).  This
includes reading and writing a variety of file formats, including, among many
others, PNG and JPEG (two formats commonly used in web publishing) as well as
common interchange formats such as PPM and TIFF.  ImageMagick 6.0.6 is known to
work with this version of ALE; certain older versions of ImageMagick may cause
compile, link, or runtime errors.  By default, support is automatically
detected.</p>

<ll>--with-imagemagick=auto  Auto-detect ImageMagick support [default]
--with-imagemagick=yes   Enable ImageMagick support
--with-imagemagick=no    Disable ImageMagick support
</ll>
</s>

<s><t>Color Data Precision</t>

<p>ALE's internal data structures store each color channel within a pixel as
floating-point data; similarly, arithmetic operations on color channels are
performed in floating point.  The available data-type configurations are
listed below, with typical data sizes indicated in parentheses.  </p>

<ll>--with-colors=single   Use C++ 'float' data type (32-bit)  [default]
--with-colors=double   Use C++ 'double' data type (64-bit)
</ll>
</s>

<s><t>
Coordinate Data Precision
</t>

<p>In general, coordinate transformations used by ALE produce results outside of
the set of integers; hence, coordinates are treated as floating-point data.
The two available data-type configurations are listed below, with typical data
sizes indicated in parentheses.</p>

<ll>--with-coords=single   Use C++ 'float' data type (32-bit)  [default]
--with-coords=double   Use C++ 'double' data type (64-bit)
</ll>
</s>

<s><t>
FFTW Support
</t>

<p>
This feature is required in order to use the --fl option; it also determines
the approach to calculation of discrete Fourier transforms used by the
Irani-Peleg renderer.  For more information on FFTW, see http://fftw.org/.
</p>

<ll>--with-fftw3=auto      Auto-detect FFTW3.  [default]
--with-fftw3=yes       Use FFTW3 discrete Fourier transform.
--with-fftw3=no        Use built-in discrete Fourier transform.
</ll>
</s>


<s><t>
Enable --wmx
</t>

<p>
This build option is required in order to use the --wmx option.  If
--enable-wmx is specified, it is expected that fork() and execlp() calls
are available.
</p>

<ll>--enable-wmx=auto      Automatically detect whether to enable --wmx
--enable-wmx=yes       Enable --wmx
--enable-wmx=no        Do not enable --wmx
</ll>
</s>

<s>
<t>Getsize</t>

<p>This build option is required to obtain additional output from --ui=tty.  If
TIOCGWINSZ is not defined in &lt;sys/ioctl.h>, however, additional output will not
be provided even if --enable-getsize is specified at build time.
</p>

<ll>--enable-getsize=auto   Check for TIOCGWINSZ at build time.  [default]
--enable-getsize=yes    Configure to attempt to use TIOCGWINSZ
--enable-getsize=no     Do not attempt to use TIOCGWINSZ
</ll>

</s>

<s><t>
Assertions
</t>

<p>
Finding bugs within ALE, or within custom modifications to ALE, can be
simplified by enabling run-time assertions.  These checks enforce conditions
believed to be necessary or desirable for correct program operation.  If a
condition is not satisfied, ALE will abort and display a message indicating the
failed assertion.
</p>

<ll>--enable-assertions    Enable assertions.  [default]
--disable-assertions   Disable assertions.
</ll>
</s>

</s>

<s><t>Cross-compilation</t>

<p>For cross-compilation, it may be necessary to specify both host and build
machine types, using the configure --host and --build options.  For more
information on these options, see the file 'INSTALL' in the source package.</p>
</s>

<s><t>Further details</t>

<p>General operation of the configure script is described in more detail in the
file 'INSTALL' in the source package.</p>

</s>
</s>

<s><t>Further Documentation</t>

<p>For information about command-line usage, program options, and program
operation, see the manuals included with the source package.  Manuals may
also be available on-line at the URL listed in the following section.</p>

</s>

<s><t>On-line resources</t>

<ll>Home Page               http://auricle.dyndns.org/ALE/
Manuals                 http://auricle.dyndns.org/ALE/manuals/
Mailing list archive    http://ventricle.dyndns.org/pipermail/ale/
</ll>

<s><t>Mailing list</t>

<p>Bug reports, feature requests, patch and release announcements, and related
discussion can be sent to ale@ventricle.dyndns.org.  Archives of past postings
and subscription information are available at the URLs indicated below.</p>

<ll>Posting address         ale@ventricle.dyndns.org
Subscription info       http://ventricle.dyndns.org/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/ale
Archives                http://ventricle.dyndns.org/pipermail/ale/
</ll>

</s>
</s>
</article>
