<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD DocBk XML V3.1.4//EN"
	"file:///usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="user-file"><title>File Output</title>

<p>File output options determine the format in which rendered images are written,
and how frequently they are written.  Depending on the compilation options used,
available file output options vary.</p>

<s><t>Output Color Depth</t>

<p>Output color depth of 8 or 16 bits of precision per color channel can be specified,
for 24-bit or 48-bit color, respectively. </p> 

<ll>
--8bpc            Write 8 bit per channel output [default]
--16bpc           Write 16 bit per channel output
</ll>
</s>

<s><t>Extension-based file type determination</t>

<p>If ALE has been built with ImageMagick support, then the output file type can
be determined automatically by file extension.  This is the default behavior
for ImageMagick builds.  The <code>--auto</code> flag explicitly specifies that
the default behavior should be used; it generates an error on builds compiled
without ImageMagick support. </p> 

<ll>
--auto            Determine file type automatically
</ll>
</s>

<s><t>PPM Output</t>

<p>All builds of ALE support PPM output.  PPM can be written in plain (ASCII) or
raw (binary) format.  If ALE has been built without ImageMagick support, or if
the file type cannot be automatically determined by file extension, then raw
PPM output is used by default.</p>

<ll>
--raw             Write raw PPM output
--plain           Write plain PPM output
</ll>
</s>

<s><t>Incremental Output</t>

<p>By default, ALE writes intermediate results periodically throughout the rendering
process.  This behavior can be disabled, however, so that output is written only
after rendering is complete.</p>

<ll>
--inc             Produce incremental output.  [default]
--no-inc          Don't produce incremental output.
</ll>
</s>

<s><t>Undefined Values [0.8.3 and later]</t>

<p>By default, ALE colors undefined values black.  To assign nearest-neighbor colors
to undefined pixels, the <code>--def-nn</code> option can be used.  This option is only
available in versions 0.8.3 and later.</p>

<ll>
--def-nn &lt;R>      Use nearest-neighbor defined values within             [0.8.3 and later]
                  radius &lt;R>, zero outside.  Default radius is 0.
		  </ll>
</s>
</chapter>
