<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD DocBk XML V3.1.4//EN"
	"file:///usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<article>


<articleinfo xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>To-do list</title>
  <abstract>This article contains a tentative list of future versions and features.</abstract>
</articleinfo>

<section><title>0.8.5</title>

<edit by="David Hilvert" in-month="2006-Sep"/>
<edit by="David Hilvert" in-month="2006-Oct"/>

<note>This release may be combined with 0.9.0.</note>
<section>
<title>
  Documentation
</title>
  <ul>
  <li>Complete migration of existing documentation from the localhost sub-directory,
    removing superfluous license terms in the footers.
  </li><li>Centralize licensing and authorship information (e.g., there should be only
    one COPYING file and only one AUTHORS file).
  </li><li>Include license and copyright terms for the doc tree Makefile
    as copyright notices in the AUTHORS and/or COPYING files (or equivalent).
  </li><li>Complete the documentation.
  </li><li>Revise the user manual for new features and syntax.
    <ul>
    <li>Document new scoping operators {}, [], and [&lt;>].
    </li><li>Document other changes in UI, including regularization of syntax.
      <ul>
      <li>in particular, commas can no longer appear in single-argument options
        when using assignment-delimited syntax; use space-delimited syntax
        instead.  This behavior is inconsistent with 0.8.4.
      </li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    </ul>
  </li><li>Add a section to the README indicating how to obtain and update source via
    darcs.
  </li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
  Website
</title>
  <ul>
  <li> Ensure consistency between the website hierarchy and the README.</li>
  </ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
  Packaging
</title>
  <section>
  <title>
    Complete Package
  </title>
<ul><li> Investigate options for distributing a 'complete' package including full
  revision history, pre-built documentation (if the ordinary distribution does
  not include this), and, possibly, example image sets.  Direct download,
  bittorrent and CD are the most prominent candidates for distribution.
  <ul>
  <li> In the case of CD distribution, information should probably be added to the
    manuals regarding how to update CD-provided program source.
  </li>
  </ul>
  </li>
  </ul>

  </section><section>
  <title>
    Windows Package
  </title>
<ul>
<li> Investigate options for creating and distributing a combined source and
  binary Windows package containing sufficient software to ensure support for
  common image types (e.g., by statically linking with libraries for opening
  JPEG and PNG files).  BitTorrent and CD are the most obvious candidates for
  distribution.
  <ul>
  <li> This package could build on the package described above, as a 'for Windows'
    variant or some such.
  </li><li> This package could make use of an application such as InstallJammer
    or Nullsoft Scriptable Install System for installation.
  </li>
  </ul>
  </li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>
	0.9.0
</title>
<edit by="David Hilvert" in-month="2006-Sep"/>
<section>
<title>
	Abstract and partial transformations
</title>
<ul>
<li>Add a generic 2D transformation class, supporting partial transformations.
  <ul><li> 'partial transformation', as used here, means that it is expected that some
    points will fail to map.
  </li></ul>
</li><li> Add a partial 2D transformation class with constructor taking as arguments
  a pair of 3D projective transformations and a 3D model.
</li></ul>
</section>

<section>
<title>
	File scoping
</title>
<ul><li> Add new file-scoped options
  <ul><li> Irani-Peleg
  </li><li> black level
  </li><li> alignment type
  </li><li> focus details
  </li></ul>
</li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
	Irani-Peleg for 3D models
</title>
<ul><li> Modify existing Irani-Peleg code to use generic (partial) 2D transformations.
  <ul><li> in combination with the above, this should allow the algorithm to operate
    on 3D models.
  </li></ul>
  </li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
	Focus bracketing for depth-of-field expansion
</title>
<ul><li> Add facilities for handling depth-of-field and focus bracketing in input
  image sets, as suggested by Viktors Rotanovs and Gregory Maxwell.  This
  change will likely involve:
  <ul><li> using the 3D model for depth data, as suggested by Gregory Maxwell
  </li><li> using user-provided (file-scoped) focus details to determine depth of field
  </li><li> using variable PSF in the Irani-Peleg algorithm, as suggested by Gregory
    Maxwell
  </li><li> developing an approach to handle the incremental (non-Irani-Peleg) case.
  </li></ul>
  </li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
Output image characteristics
</title>
<ul><li>Allow specification of output image characteristics, including exposure
(e.g., gamma) and channel offsets within a pixel.
  </li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
Output devices
</title>
<ul><li>Add support for specifying output devices, such as LCD monitors, to
allow shorthand customization of exposure (e.g., gamma) and other
characteristics, such as channel offset in the case of LCD screens for sub-pixel
anti-aliasing.
  </li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
Weight and certainty upper bounds
</title>
<ul><li>Add support for specifying weight and certainty upper bounds for
rendering, either as an absolute constraint or relative to average
weights, so that the overall contributions to an output pixel (or channel) are
constrained by weight.  

  </li></ul>
</section>

<section>
<title>
Time locality
</title>
<ul><li>In combination with weight and certainty upper bounds, time locality could be
used to determine which frames are used to generate an output pixel.  As a
special case of this, video stream processing could favor frames
having the smallest time difference from the target frame.
  </li></ul>
</section>

<section>
<title>
	Multi-threading
</title>
<ul><li> Add multi-threading options (e.g., for rendering code), so that a single
  invocation of the program can run on multiple processors simultaneously.
</li></ul>
</section>
</section>



<section>
<title>
	1.0.0 (Stable)
</title>
<edit by="David Hilvert" in-month="2006-Sep"/>
<section>
<title>
	Performance
</title>
<ul><li> Refine rendering and alignment code for better performance.
  </li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
	Internationalization
</title>
<ul><li> Enhance the command-line interface in preparation for i18n.  (?)
  <ul><li> e.g., syntax for identifying synchronized frame sets
  </li></ul>
</li><li> Internationalize the command-line interface and help text to accommodate
  translations.
  </li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
	Technical Manual Updates
</title>
<ul><li> Update the Technical Manual for information regarding 3D operation.
</li></ul>
</section>
</section>



<section>
<title>
	Unsorted
</title>
<edit by="David Hilvert" in-month="2006-Sep"/>
<edit by="David Hilvert" in-month="2006-Oct"/>
<section>
<title>
	Documentation
</title>
<ul><li> Generate correctly indented book-level tables of contents when rendering
the complete set of manuals.
  </li><li>Add a tutorial, and credit Metin Toyran for suggesting a step-by-step
    guide.
  </li><li> Remedy meaningless page numbers for book title pages in the set
  ToC.
</li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
	Integer-value routines
</title>
<ul><li> Add facilities for manipulating images storing color as integer-valued data,
  possibly as library routines.
</li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
	Library
</title>
<ul><li> Move image-processing routines into a library that can be used by other 
  programs.
</li></ul>
</section>
<section>
<title>
	Language Bindings
</title>
<ul><li> Add bindings for other programming languages.
</li></ul>
</section>
</section>



</article>
